Guide to the Woman's College Library records, 1930-1994, bulk 1930-1970.
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Woman's College Library records 1930-1994, bulk 1930-1970.
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Woman's College. Library.
1.0 Linear Feet 1,000 Items
The Woman's College Library dates from the 1927 construction of the Woman's College campus. During the three years required to build the library on West Campus, this was the library for the entire university. In 1930 the Woman's College Library opened officially with a collection of 4,000 books.
The collection contains material pertaining to the operations of the Woman's College Library including clippings, correspondence, and periodical subscriptions. The major topic in the collection is art exhibits. Materials date from 1930-1994, bulk 1930-1970.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Woman's College Library records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1966-1993.
Historical Note
from The Library of the Woman's College, Duke University, 1930-1972 by Betty Irene Young.
The Woman's College Library began its operations on September 24, 1930. Designed primarily for the new coordinate college, the new library on East Campus (completed in March 1927) served as the interim university library until 1930 when the main library on West Campus was completed. While serving as the main Duke library the future Woman's College Library housed over one hundred thousand volumes transferred from the previous library; a number that would more than double over the next three years as the collection grew to meet the demands of the developing university. When the main collection transferred over to West Campus in 1930 the number of volumes dramatically dwindled as the Woman's College Library was left with approximately 4,000 new books "selected with special reference to the needs of the Coordinate College for Women."
The first librarian of the Woman's College Library, Lillian Baker Griggs (1930-1949), believed that a college library should promote "the love of books and libraries in the heart of the average student to such an extent that a library will be necessary to a contented life." She began by making the library an inviting place citing a plan "to give the library certain distinctly feminine touches which have hitherto been lacking on campus." The Woman's College Library became known for its Booklover Room with its browsable collection, and informal atmosphere which later led the way to regular teas and evening talks by professors.
The librarians worked hard during the first couple of years to triple the holdings, and soon the collection numbered over twelve thousand. They also devised collection strengths in education, art, juvenile literature, literature, music, history, and psychology through both buying new material and recalling back volumes that had previously been transferred to the main library. Over the forty-two years that the coordinated college for women existed at Duke, art and the Woman's College Library became inextricably linked. Art objects were displayed throughout the building, and the library hosted numerous exhibitions.
In 1972 the Board of Trustees approved the merger of the Woman's College and Trinity College. The Woman's College Library became known as the East Campus Library. The library was renamed Lilly Library in 1990 in recognition of a generous gift from Miss Ruth Lilly. The library underwent extensive renovations in 1993, and today (2007) houses the collections for the visual arts, art history, philosophy, and theater studies, and has services geared especially to the first-year experience.
Collection Overview
Collection contains material pertaining to the operations of the Woman's College Library including clippings, correspondence, and periodical subscriptions. The major topic in the collection is art exhibits including: announcements of art exhibitions; booklets on works of art; biographical sketches of artists; and schedules of exhibitions. Materials date from 1930-1994, bulk 1930-1970.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Art -- 20th century -- Exhibitions
Duke University. Woman’s College. Library
Duke University. Library
Duke University. Library -- History.
Clippings
Exhibition catalogs.
Related Material
Art Association Records, bulk 1930 - 1938.
University Archives, Duke University.
Arts Council Records, 1950 - 1970.
University Archives, Duke University.
Lillian Baker Griggs Papers, 1930-1949
University Archives, Duke University.
William R. Perkins Library of Duke University.
University Archives, Duke University.
Woman’s College records, 1928-1974.
University Archives, Duke University.
The Library of the Woman’s College, Duke University, 1930-1972.
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 2 Boxes
  - Clippings, 1935-1983, bulk 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, General, 1936-1951
  - Correspondence, Martins Nijhoff Modern and Antiquarian Bookseller, 1939-1940
  - Correspondence, Joseph Ruzicka Bookbinder, Greensboro, NC 1941-1951
  - General, 1934-1978
    The General folder includes the Woman College's Library buying policy, proposed budgets, correspondence, committee records, study guides for students, and a student paper (1971) examining the operations of the Woman's College Library.
  - Joseph Ruzicka, Price Quotations for binding, 1947-1960
  - Periodicals, subscription binding, 1949-1970
  - Periodical Subscriptions Lists, 1930-1946 (2 folders)
  - Periodical Selection, suggestions of committees, 1934-1940
  - Periodicals, volumes needed for completion, 1946-1947
  - Psychology Periodicals, 1936-1961
  - Exhibits, 1930-1973 (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Library/Study Guides, 1957-1994